<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jeffrey Herrera | Designer</title>
    <description>Portfolio of Jeffrey Herrera.
</description>
    <link>http://jeffreyherrera.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://jeffreyherrera.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 07:00:54 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 07:00:54 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is it because I&#39;m pretty?</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;foreword&quot;&gt;
This is a response to a quote from an article by Michael Bierut for The Design Observer. Although I take a very specific and opinionated stance on this, it is just that, my opinion. It is imperative to read the article yourself and come to your own conclusion.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Find it here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://designobserver.com/feature/george-kennan-and-the-cold-war-between-form-and-content/1977/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;George Kennan and the cold war between form and content&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The graphic designer’s role is largely one of giving form to content.
Often — perhaps even nearly always — this process is a cosmetic exercise. 
Only rarely does the form of a message become a signal of meaning in and of 
itself.”   — Michael Bierut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When discussing the idea of “cosmetics,” I believe that there are far too many definitions and connections we make to experiences or other parts of life for it to be an appropriate word to use. Throughout our lifetime, everything we see and learn builds our visual library. This visual library, constantly growing, is subconsciously brought out for reference as we go through everyday life. The word cosmetic itself has ties to industries and applications that call for judgment before analysis. If, in this case, we are going to discuss cosmetics as purely visual and separate from concept, then I believe Bierut may be undermining the nods we as graphic designers give to our content in connection to its form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point in time, it is more rare for me to come across graphic design as being purely cosmetic exercise because of the distinction that professional graphic designers have had to make between themselves and amateur designers. Being that Bierut wrote the piece in 2004, there is the chance that this need for separation of professional and amateur has exponentially raised, but as it stands today; form relating to content is what separates the groups. Any person can achieve a “purely cosmetic exercise” in today’s world with Internet access and slight knowledge of piracy. This type of exercise no longer works independently in the field of design as it has been appropriated for things such as tutorials and what I like to call “drone design.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;drone-design&quot;&gt;Drone Design&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My idea of drone design is that which takes a technical method, such as a new tool or algorithm in technology, and makes it into a working piece just to prove the concept of the tool. This approach is very systematic. It is based upon proving feasibility, and does not respond to content. Rather, it speaks to the technique and meant to be repurposed. Rarely does drone design give the satisfaction that comes with a real thought out approach. Now, our jobs as professional designers, is to take the content provided and have it speak as a form instead of &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; a form. This, admittedly, may be directly connected to a designer’s training. Bringing form to content and having them live together is the easy part. Taking the content itself and making it communicate visually, however, is in my opinion, what designers are meant to do. It is not enough for a professional graphic designer to create a composition and then add content; we create ideas around the content and fuse them together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we evolve into the world of smaller, digital screens and faster paced content creation, our design is required to speak more clearly and direct. This necessity brings to light the importance of visual form directly relating to, and making use of, the content that it is representing. To fragment that connection means to fragment the message being conveyed. Thus, turning what should be a direct and impactful form of communication into a battle for attention. Masterfully put together and deliberate conflict on the page (the word page used loosely to represent the container of the design) can yield beautiful and interesting compositions. However, if it does not relate to the content it loses not only impact but also purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-talk-on-purpose&quot;&gt;A talk on purpose.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Content precedes design. Design in the absence of content is not design, 
it’s decoration” — Jeffrey Zeldman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we determine the success of our job, if it is centered around creativity? I believe that purpose answers this question. With every piece of work that we are asked to create, there must be a specific reason or “purpose” for it to exist. Fulfilment of this established purpose determines the success or failure of the creative. Whether we get this purpose from the client or determine it as the project goes along, it becomes the center of which we base every aspect of the work as a whole. As Jeffrey Zeldman states, content precedes design because there is no complete design if it is not anchored by the content it represents. In the case of cosmetics, to me, it shares the same definition as Zeldman’s idea of decoration. We are thinkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason we exist as professionals is to bring together content and cosmetics. Treating them as separate entities defies what we set out to do as thinkers. The parity of the two, is design. The treatment of cosmetics without content is mere exercise. There is a case to be made for cosmetic practice or as I call it, “drone design.” as it relates to learning a craft. Take the example of plumbing. A plumber can learn to use the tools and ins and outs of solving a problem technically and logically; but there is very little need for abstracted or even unique trains of thought when working on something as technical. This is cosmetics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we begin our process with thought, there is a very low chance of failure because at that point, the cosmetics are so deeply rooted in the content that it becomes almost foolproof. It works in a way that any approach to relative visuals only makes the concept stronger. Striking this balance is what we as professional designers are striving for. In order to acknowlege the necessity for this balance, we must first go in a different direction than Bierut’s idea of cosmetics and form. and treat them as equals never to be separated. Granted, the article in which Bierut made these claims was published in a very different time than when this is being written, but the basis of design has always been adding idea and purpose to visuals. What separates a designer and a fine artist, in my opinion, is this purpose. The need for a certain thing to be resolved and rooted in an interlinking thought process. This will continue to be more prevalent as we dive deeper into the new age of content creation and multi-display visual representation. We are being brought into a world where cosmetics and form live in a place that is much more confined yet equally as vast and flexible than it has ever been. Not only do we need to make our necessary technical adjustments for things to fit and look visually correct across these screens (cosmetic), but we have to make the idea and relation of form to content that much stronger and more consice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now more than ever, designers must look for ways to communicate with enough efficiency to work at both a glance and stare. Both a billboard and handheld device. Although the gamut is quickly expanding, there is an opportunity to streamline the design process by starting with the solid, irrefutable idea.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://jeffreyherrera.com/Is-it-because-I'm-pretty</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jeffreyherrera.com/Is-it-because-I'm-pretty</guid>
        
        
        <category>design</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What Helvetica taught me about personal relationships.</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;oh-the-almighty-helvetica&quot;&gt;Oh, the almighty Helvetica.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed by Max Miedinger (props to you too, Eduard Hoffman &lt;em&gt;power fist emoji&lt;/em&gt;), Helvetica is the praised typeface of modern graphic design. It was modeled loosely after our …err, okay, my beloved Akzidenz-Grotesk, among other things. Designed to be neutral, incredibly clear and void of any natural applied meaning it was the face of choice for things like signage and many corporate logos. If we ran down the list of all the times it has been used, we would be here forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that is not what we are here to discuss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my work life I began to see a growing dependency on Helvetica. It was trustworthy. It was always there when I needed. At the very least, it would get me through the day. &lt;strong&gt;That’s why I had to let it go.&lt;/strong&gt; It was not Helvetica’s fault. Good old Helv was not hiding its utility and, in fact, it was laying everything out on the table. “This is who I am, these are my characteristics, and this is what my creator meant for me to be.” I knew what it was there for. I knew its history. But, I was trying to use it for things that it never offered me. I was searching for Helvetica to get me out of prolonging my journey on the job and provide an “out” on any given day. I could not bear the thought of research. That is to say that I could not see myself spending time looking for something more appropriate for that moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;it-made-me-lazy&quot;&gt;It made me lazy.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lazy in the sense that I knew better. In all actuality, I knew that I knew better. Helvetica was not going to take me to the next level, but it was most definitely going to satisfy the current criteria and guarantee comfort. Once I made myself realize what I was doing, it was like turning a corner in a labyrinth that I had been trapped in for months and seeing the exit. Everything became clear. I needed to take the long way. I needed to study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I could no longer mold Helvetica. I would no longer mold Helvetica…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;…because it never asked me to.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://jeffreyherrera.com/What-Helvetica-taught-me-about-personal-relationships</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jeffreyherrera.com/What-Helvetica-taught-me-about-personal-relationships</guid>
        
        
        <category>design</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
